Wonderful. He has advanced even more than expected.
（フンガ）すばらしい！
予想以上の成長です。
（ビショップ）大門カイトとシンクロし　オルペウスの
腕輪も　反応を増幅させています。
The Armband of Orpheus has synced with him and its effects are amplifying.
（ダイスマン）
すべては　ルーク様の思惑どおりっす。
It's all going according to Sir Rook's plan.
（ルーク）プロジェクトを
ネクストシークエンスに移行する。
The project will now shift to the next sequence.
（ダイスマン）えっ？！　それは　まだ
早いんじゃないっすかね？
Isn't it a bit too early?
（メイズ）そのようなことをして
大門カイトに　もしもの事があれば…。
If we did that and by chance something happened to Daimon Kaito...
（フンガ）ピタゴラス伯爵のご判断を
仰ぐべきかと？
Shouldn't we inquire Count Pythagoras's opinion?
パズルを解いているときの君は
すてきだよ…　カイト。
You are truly wonderful when solving puzzles, Kaito.
（ノノハ）カイト…　カイト…　カイト！
Kaito! Kaito!
Kaito!
起きろ！　この三年寝太郎！
Wake up, you creepy sleepyhead!
kimi no nounai he shinnyuu nemutteiru sukima ni
I infiltrate your brain while you're sleeping.
Baby, open the gate!
fukuzatsu sugi sekyuriti kakusareru to abakitaku naru
The security's too tough, but I want to expose what's hidden.
barabara ni chirabatteiru pasuwado wo hiroi atsume
I gather the pieces of the shattered password.
kakushin ni sematte iku sono shoutai wo misete
I get close to the core. Show me who you really are!
kantan ni kuria dekinai saki nante motto yomenai
I can't clear it easily. I can't even see what lies ahead.
kaidoku fukanou sumairu kikenna pazuru
Your indecipherable smile is a hazardous puzzle.
rokku sareta doa aru nara zutto tataite miru beki kazana hiraku wa
When you see a locked door, you should just hit it until a crack opens.
eien ni hodokenai nazo nanka wa nai
There's no mystery that lasts forever!
makiokosu, it's a supernova
I made it, it's a supernova!
tobikiri shigekitekina hirameki wo agemashou
Let's flash so bright it'd hurt!
Misskey-Misskey La-Tu-Ma
yume no naka it's a supernova
In my dreams, it's a supernova!
watashi wa sou brain diver
Yeah, I'm the brain diver!
kimi ga sagashi motometeru kotae ni nareru made
Until I can find the answer you're looking for...
Brain diver!
Puzzle Time of Reunion
痛ててて！　…ったく
なんつ～　起こし方だよ！
Ouch... Why did you have to wake me up like that?
カイトが起きないからでしょう？！
Maybe because you wouldn't get out of the bed?
おかげで　ケガが絶えねえや。
なんか言った？！
Thanks to you I always have a few bruises.
What was that?
ほう！
ダメ。　アナが解くの。
No, I'll solve it!
（ソウジ）カイト君と行動を
ともにするようになって→
Cubic and Ana have both changed since they joined Kaito.
キュービック君もアナ君も変わりました。
Maybe the talent of the children of the Phi Brain is awakening?
ファイ・ブレインの子供たちとして→
その才能が
目覚め始めたのかもしれません。
As a Solver, Kaito is showing remarkable progress as well.
カイト君も　ソルヴァーとして
目覚ましい成長を遂げた。
学園長の方針は危険すぎると
思うこともありました。
I did think your methods were a bit too dangerous.
しかし…　ん？！
どうしたのですか？
But...
What's wrong?
（バロン）ヘルベルト・ミューラーが
更迭されたことは話しましたね。
I told you about Herbert Müller's replacement, right?
はい。
前の総責任者が復帰したと…。
Yes, something about the previous chief returning...
見てください。
Look at this.
ＰＯＧジャパンからの指令書…。
An order from the POG...
はぁ　これは？！
This...
Morning!
おはよう！
あ～っす。　あっ？！
Hey.
ん？！　何　これ？
（女子Ａ）さあ？
What's this?
Dunno.
（女子Ｂ）来たときには
もう書いてあったけど。
It was there when we got here.
落書き？　子供じゃあるまいし。
It's someone's doodling? Seriously, we're not kids anymore.
あっ　待て！
ん。　えっ？！
Wait!
カイト…。
Kaito?
パズルだったの？
これは…　このパズルは…。
It was a puzzle?
I know this puzzle...
（ルーク）覚えていてくれたんだね。
ん。　あっ。
You remembered it.
Have you forgotten me?
僕のことは　忘れちゃったかな。
As if I would... As if I could!
忘れるか…　忘れるもんかよ！
体は　もう　大丈夫なのか？
Have you recovered?
うん。　カイトも元気そうだね。
Yeah. I see you're doing well too.
Is that a Cross Field Academy uniform?
その制服…　クロスフィールド学院の？
あれから　また戻って
今は高等部に通ってる。
Yeah, after what happened, I returned there to finish high school.
（男子Ａ）
クロスフィールド学院って　世界中の
天才が集まるっていう　あの？
Cross Field? You mean that international genius school?
（男子Ｂ）カイトって　そんなやつと
知り合いなのかよ？
Kaito knows someone from there?
えっ？！　じゃあ…　ねぇ　カイト！
Uh, but... Hey, Kaito, is he the one you told me about earlier?
その子　ひょっとして
前に話してた…　あっ！
ルーク！
あああっ。
Rook!
ハッ。
ルーク！　ルーク！
Rook! Rook!
この野郎　脅かしやがって！
あぁ　ごめん　ごめん。
You surprised me so much!
Sorry!
How long's it been?
何年ぶりだよ。
あぁ　きゅっ　９年かな？
Nine years, I think.
（２人）ヘヘヘッ。
で？　何で　こんな所に居んだよ？
And, what are you doing here?
まさか　俺に会いに来たって
わけじゃねえよな。
Don't tell me you came all this way just to see me.
その　まさかだよ。
マジかよ！
But that's exactly the case.
You're kidding!
No. You have been chosen for a short-term scholarship at England's Crossfield Academy.
はい。　イギリスのクロスフィールド学院への
短期留学生に君が選ばれましてね。
（ルーク）
で　僕が迎えに来たってわけ。
And I'm here to pick you up.
But to think you two were acquainted...
それにしても　まさか　カイト君と
ルーク君が知り合いだったとは…。
I told you about a guy in England who made amazing puzzles, right?
話したことあったよな。　イギリスに
すげえパズル　作るやつがいたって。
こいつが　その　すげえやつさ！
Here he is!
He's one amazing dude!
You're way better, Kaito.
カイトには　かなわないよ。
なぁに　言ってやがる！
What are you talking about?!
え～っ？！　イギリス～？！
England?!
Why are you so surprised?
…んな　驚くこっちゃねえだろ。
行くも　なにも　俺は
ずっと住んでたんだぜ。
I lived there for a long time.
まっ　里帰りみてえなもんかな。
It's like I'm going home.
そのまま向こうに　居ついちまえば
いいんじゃねえの？
Then you should just stay over there!
No! Not that!
（キュービック）そんなの　ダメ～！
He's the chief of POG Japan.
心の声
彼がＰＯＧジャパンの総責任者…。
And...
心の声
そして…。
What is the meaning of this?
（バロン）どういうことでしょうか？
To the best of my knowledge, Phi Brain education is our job at Section Phi.
ファイ・ブレイン育成は　我々
セクションΦの管轄のはずです。
Project oversight has been given to Rook Banjo Crossfield.
（ビショップ）プロジェクトの指揮権は
ルーク・盤城・クロスフィールド管理官へと→
移行しました。
あっ。
（ビショップ）管理官は　ピタゴラス伯爵より
すべてを一任されております。
All authority has been given to him by Count Pythagoras.
（ルーク）友達が
いっぱいできたみたいだね。
Looks like you have many friends.
（ギャモン・カイト）何？！
友達？
…んなんじゃねえよ。
What?!
Friends?!
The hell we are. How did you conclude we were friends?!
（ギャモン）どこを　どう見たら　俺と
こいつが友達に見えんだよ！
こんなやつとは　友達どころか
知り合いですらねぇ！
We're not even acquaintances, no less friends!
カイトとルークは　お友達なの？
はっ？
You and Rook are friends, Kaito?
ああ…。
（ルーク）カイトが　ご両親を亡くしてね。
Yeah...
Kaito lost his parents, you know.
解道バロン氏に引き取られたカイトは
クロスフィールド学院に留学してきたんだ。
Mr. Kaido Baron took him in, and he studied for a while at Crossfield Academy.
そこで…。
And there...
あぁ…　あの…　一緒に…。
回想
Umm... Can we...?
回想　（生徒たち）あっち行こうぜ。
あいつ　すぐ　パズル解いちゃうし。
Let's go over there.
He solves them right away, it's boring.
つまんないんだよな。
回想
So cool!
カッコいい！
うっ。
回想
カッコいいパズルだね。
僕にやらせて。
Your puzzle's so cool! Let me solve it!
We spent our lunch breaks together after that.
（ルーク）それから毎日
昼休みは一緒に過ごした。
I made the puzzles, and he solved them.
僕がパズルを作って　カイトが解いて。
回想
（ルーク）また明日ね　カイト。
See you tomorrow, Kaito.
Yeah...
When the break was over, he vanished.
昼休みが終わるたびに
どこかへ消えちまう。
全寮制の学校だっていうのに
寮にも居ねえ。
We all lived in a dorm, but he wasn't there either.
初めは幽霊かと思ったぜ。
At first, I thought you were a ghost!
体が弱くて
特別教室にいたからね。
I took special classes because my body was weak.
だから　僕も独りぼっちで。
So I was alone as well.
カイトと友達になれて
本当にうれしかった。
I'm glad we became friends.
Me too.
俺もだ。
なのに　お前は転校しちまって…。
But then you changed schools.
（ルーク）また会えて　うれしいよ　カイト。
I'm glad we could meet again.
また　お前のパズルを
解けるなんてな　ルーク。
I'm looking forward to solving your puzzles again.
美しき友情ってか。
This is a beautiful friendship?
あとで連絡するからよ。
（ルーク）うん。　じゃあ…。
I'll call you later then.
Okay, bye.
帰ったら　早速　荷造りしねえとな。
I should get down to packing.
待ってよ　カイト！
Wait, Kaito!
心の声
あんな　うれしそうな顔
初めて見た。
I've never seen him so happy.
カイトのことは　全部
分かってるつもりだったのにな。
I thought I knew everything about him.
ん？！　どうしたの？
What's wrong?
あの子とカイト　ホントに
仲よしさんなのかな？
えっ？！
Are Kaito and that guy actually good friends?
アナが思うに　２人は遠すぎる。
カイトは青い太陽。　あの子は赤い月。
I think... they are too far apart.
Kaito is a blue sun. He is a red moon.
青い太陽と赤い月？
A blue sun and a red moon?
総責任者とカイト君が
親友同士だったなんて…。
So the Chief and Kaito were friends...
すぐそばにいたのです。
ありえない話ではありません。
They were both there, so it is not impossible.
しかし　なぜ　カイト君を　イギリスへ？
But why would he take Kaito to England?
君は　もっと強く　美しくなれる。
You can get stronger and more beautiful.
一緒に行こう　カイト。
Let's go together, Kaito.
（キュービック）あ～あ！　行っちゃった。
Ah, he left...
ふう！　でも　僕からは
逃げられないからね。
But he can't get away from me!
カイト…。
Kaito...
…って　ノノハスイーツ！　いつの間に！
What?! Nonoha sweets?! When did she...?!
うぅ。　ベストのポケットにまで入ってる。
Even my vest pockets are full of them!
こ　これは　アナかな？
Th-This is from Ana?
お帰り　カイト。
ふっ。
Welcome home, Kaito.
お前もな。　お帰り　ルーク。
You too. Welcome home, Rook.
あれ　まだ　あんだな！
That's still here?
ここは…。
僕がいた特別教室さ。
This is...
This is the special class I've been attending.
回想
（ルーク）また明日ね。
See you tomorrow!
君が　僕の支えだった。
君だけが…。
You supported me. You alone.
俺だけじゃねえだろ？
It wasn't just me...
あの人も居たじゃねえか。
He was there as well.
そうだね。　ねぇ　行ってみようか？
あの場所へ。
You're right.
How about going there?
あの場所？
Where?
回想
どこへ行くの？
いいから来いよ！
Where are we going?
Just come with me!
回想
えいっ。
あぁ。
（２人）ハァ　ハァ。
ここは　あの時も来た教会。
It's the church from back then.
回想
（ルーク）これって　もしかして…。
Is this...?
Yeah, a maze!
回想
ああ　迷路さ。
This way?
回想
こっちかな？
ううん。　こっちじゃないかな。
No, this way.
回想
（２人）ヘヘヘッ！
フフフッ。　何度もチャレンジしたよな。
We challenged it a lot.
うん。　なかなか　ゴールに
たどりつけなくて→
We couldn't find the goal, and got lost one day...
ある日　ついに迷っちゃって…。
回想
うっ。
泣くな！
Don't cry!
But they'll get mad at me if I'm not home soon.
回想
でも　早く帰らないと
怒られちゃう。
回想
（小石の転がる音）
あっ！　誰だ？！
Who's there?!
回想
（カイト・ルーク）あ～！
うぅ。
（青年Ｘ）君は…。
You're...
回想
俺だよ。　忘れちまったのか？
It's me! Have you forgotten me?
回想
あぁ！
妙な所で　また会ったな。
Heh, we meet in a weird place again!
回想
こっちだ。
うん。
This way.
回想
（２人）ハァハァハァ。
どうした？
こんなの初めて見た。
What is it?
It's the first time I've seen something like this.
回想
（ルーク）きれいだな！
It's so beautiful!
回想
ありがとうございました！
Thank you very much!
回想
大切なものは
手放さなかったようだな。
You didn't let go of what's important.
回想
あぁ　あの　僕　大門カイト！
Um, I'm Daimon Kaito.
回想
あぁ　ルークです。
Uh, I'm Rook!
回想
そうだな。　じゃあ　俺は　青年Ｘで。
Let's see... Then I'm Youth X!
回想
えっ？！
せ　青年Ｘ？！
Youth X?
Yeah! It's cool, isn't it?
回想
そっ　カッコいいだろ？
ホント　変わった人だったぜ。
He was a really strange person.
（ルーク）でも　いろんなことを
教えてくれた。
Even so, he taught us a lot of stuff.
It's puzzle time!
回想
さあ　パズルタイムの始まりだ。
パズルを見ると　それを
作った人のことも分かるんだ。
Looking at a puzzle, you can understand the feelings of the person who made it.
回想
パズルとの出会いは
人との出会い。
When you encounter a puzzle, you encounter a person.
回想
カイト　解いてやれ。
Kaito... Solve them.
Free them.
自由にしてやれ。
回想
不幸なパズルたちを。
Those unhappy puzzles.
あの人がいたから…　俺は…。
It's because he was there...
（ルーク）カイト。
ん？
Kaito.
どうしたんだよ？
こんな所に　こんな道あったっけ？
What's up?
Was there a path like this?
いや　覚えてねえけど。
No, not if I remember correctly.
なんだ…　この感じ？
What's this feeling?
あれ　なんだろ？
ん？
What's that?
戻ろう。　おかしな気配を感じる。
Let's go back. This feels weird.
こいつは「賢者のパズル」かも
しれねえ。　だとしたら　危険だ。
This might be a Sage Puzzle, and that's dangerous.
賢者のパズルって　あの？
Sage Puzzle? Is that...
知ってるのか？！
噂くらいはね。
You know them?
All too well.
古代の権力者たちが
自らの財を封印した結界で→
Ancient powerful men locked their treasures in barriers,
いつか　それにふさわしい人物が
現れ→
which contained the wish that someday, someone worthy would come to claim the prize.
財を手にしてほしいという
願いが込められている。
でも　どうして　それが危険なの？
悪意の塊みてえな→
But why are they dangerous?
There are ones like a heap of evil, built only to hurt others.
人を傷つけるために
作られたようなものもあるんだよ。
Isn't that just to prevent unworthy ones from claiming it?
ふさわしくない人間に
財を渡さないためにでしょ？
多少の危険は
しかたないんじゃないかな？
A bit of danger is reasonable, isn't it?
You can only say that because you've never solved one.
お前は解いたことがねえから
んなこと　言えんだ。
カイトは　あるの？
何度も　死にかけたぜ。
Have you?
They tried to kill me several times.
全部　悪意に満ちたものだったの？
そ　それは…。
Were they all full of evil?
W-Well...
昔　カイトに言ったよね？
悪いのは　パズルじゃないって！
I told you long ago, didn't I? It's not the puzzles' fault.
覚えてる？
Do you remember?
Yeah.
回想
（ルーク）悪いのは　パズルじゃない。
It's not the puzzle's fault!
回想
裏切るのは　いつでも
それを作った人間。
It's always the person who made it that betrays us.
（ルーク）正しい人間が作った
「賢者のパズル」なら→
Then isn't there no problem with Sage Puzzles made by good people?
問題ないんじゃないかな？
But those puzzles still hurt people!
それでも　人を傷つける
パズルなんてよ！
Let's try solving it.
解いてみようよ。
やめろ！
Stop!
危険なパズルじゃ
ないかもしれない。
It might not be dangerous.
And what if it is?
危険だったら　どうする？！
出会ったパズルは解くって
約束をしたんじゃなかったの？
You promised you'd solve all puzzles you face!
パズルを自由にしてあげるって。
約束したんでしょ？　あの人と。
You promised him you'd free the puzzles!
このパズルも
待ってるのかもしれないよ。
This puzzle could be waiting for you as well.
誰かが解いてくれるのを。
For someone to solve it.
悪いのは　人間なんだ。
パズルに罪はない。
It's always the maker's fault. The puzzle does nothing wrong.
解いてあげようよ　カイト。
Solve it, Kaito.
パズルを自由にしてあげよう。
Make it free.
（外す音）
フッ。　パズルタイムの始まりだ。
It's puzzle time.
（扉が閉まる音）
あっ！　ルーク！　どこだ？！　ルーク！
Rook! Where are you, Rook?!
This way!
こっちか！
（回転ノコギリの音）
Shit! I don't have time to think!
クソッ！　考える時間もねぇ。
後戻りもさせねえってことかよ！
It won't let me turn back!
（バロン）イギリスのセクションΦの
メンバーから　連絡がありました。
I have been contacted by a member of England's Section Phi.
どうやら　カイト君は　パズルに…。
「賢者のパズル」にですか？！
It seems Kaito challenged a puzzle.
A Sage Puzzle?
いいえ。
では　一体？
No.
Then, what is it?
What is this place? This murderous intent!
心の声
なんだ　こいつは？
この殺気。
Something's different from the previous Sage Puzzles!
心の声
今までの賢者のパズルとは
何かが…！
（バロン）ファイ・ブレインを育てるために
特化された→
It's a horrid, forbidden puzzle developed for the sole purpose of
忌まわしき禁断のパズル…。
developing the Phi brain.
あそこが　ゴールか！
That's the goal?!
ここは…。
This is...
...a Fools' Puzzle.
（バロン）愚者のパズルに…。
tsukue no ue de umareta sekai
This world born on my table.
ichiban saki ni kimi ni misetakatta
I wanted you to see it first.
karappo no heya sotto nukedashite hashiri hajimeteta
I sneaked out of the empty room and started to run.
iki hazamasete oka wo noboru to
As I got to the top of the hill, out of breath,
kimi ga saki ni tsuite matteita ne
you were already there waiting for me.
takusan no hajimete kimi to mitsuketa takaramono datta
It was the first of many treasures we would find together.
kanashisa de afureta toki wa
When sorrow was overflowing in me,
nanimo iwazu ni tada soba ni ite kureta ne
you just silently stayed by my side.
ima de mo wasurenai yo
I still haven't forgotten that.
mata aou ne yakusoku wo shiyou
Let's promise we'll meet again.
kie wa shinai ano hi no sayonara
The goodbye of that day we'll never forget.
boku no subete kimi ga kureta michi
All I have I got from you,
zutto kokoro no naka hikaru yo
and it will all shine in my heart forever.